soft engineering radio episode 113
building platforms with Jeff McCaffrey
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
I see radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every 10
days thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website possible
[Music]
so welcome listeners to another episode
on softening radio in this episode we
are going to talk about building
platforms and we have invited a guest
Jeff McCafferty to this episode I'm so
welcome Jeff to soften engineer a deal
would you like to introduce yourself to
our listeners sure well as you say my
name is Jeff McCaffrey and I'm one of
the the original folks on the Eclipse
project you know I've been around it
since before it was Eclipse and I
focused mostly on runtime level things
you know the equinox OSGi implementation
i'm the RCP rich client platform lead
and I also lead Equinox project and a
few other projects and I'm on a few
PMC's in the eclipse Board of Directors
so I kind of do a lot of things around
eclipse in a fairly varied way but it
yeah and I recently started a company
around Eclipse called code 9 and we do a
number of things and in kind of the
areas that we're going to talk about
today ok cool
so welcome again to self imaging radio I
think we we we can just start with with
it with the topic of this episode I'm
building platforms so maybe before we
discuss how to build a platform we can
talk about what is a platform can you
give us a short term short definition or
an impression from your point of view
what is a platform sure sure we've been
doing you know platforms for quite a
while you know obviously eclipse itself
is sort of one large platform and you
know I don't think we've come up with a
scientific definition of the term or
anything like that but it seems like it
really comes down to it being all of the
you know the Gorp if you will all the
stuff in the middle that you need to
have to solve your application or solve
your problem but you don't actually want
to write yourself so it's almost like
middleware in the classic sense of the
term it's all the things that you want
to build on top of the functionality and
the components that you take and put
together to build your application
system so many people think they think
about it clips as the Eclipse Java IDE
and stuff like that so can you can you
give us a brief impression
what the difference is between a
platform and an application yeah it's
interesting actually because the you
know the application is is what you
typically see is the end-user and the
application may or may not be
implemented based on a platform so the
IDE that the Java IDE that you mentioned
is in fact based on a relatively generic
IDE platform and then it with a bunch of
the Java stuff glued on top of it and so
the the idea here is that the platform
is relatively generic it's a set of
functionality that you can compose and
use but the application is a particular
composition of that functionality
perhaps with some additional pieces that
go together as I say to to address a
particular problem in your example the
problem of how to develop java code so
making a java ide but other people will
take that same function let straight
that same platform and compose other
functionality with it to build a C IDE
right and then other people will take
even you know below the IDE platform is
a rich client platform and people will
take that and and compose it with other
functionality to make a an application
for banking or for controlling space
missions or you know a wide variety of
things I remember people talking about
I'm this kind of of infrastructure
components and as frameworks so white
box frameworks and black box frameworks
are they I think they they're they get
very famous in the the object oriented
i'm space so what do you think is there
a distinction between a framework and a
platform
yeah I mean I certainly hear people
talking about and you know same oh is
that a platform or a framework and and
you know in historically we haven't paid
much attention to that sort of
distinction I think we have implicitly
but we don't sort of walk around talking
about talking about it explicitly and
the way I look at these things as
relatively informally and and talk about
you know platforms as being like I said
collections of functionality that you
can put together to solve a problem and
it's something you build on top of you
know if you look at the English meanings
of the word platform versus framework
you know a platform is something that
you sort of stand on and you build upon
and you do things on top of and a
framework tends to be more inclusive or
prescriptive and as much as it kind of
surrounds you and it provides you an
environment and wit in which you work
not on top of which you work and there's
no good or bad here there's no right or
wrong I think both are essential
elements of a good software system and
in fact many platforms and much of
Eclipse is built as a composition of
frameworks if you will you look at
equinox the runtime that's underlying
Eclipse itself you know it's an OS geo
and implementation the OSGi standard and
the UI community talks about that as a
framework they call it the framework and
also in eclipse you'll see you know
within the UI lots of different
frameworks framework for the whole
perspective notion you know perspectives
with views perspectives fit inside of a
window there's all these facilities that
the UI provides you that you just sort
of hook into and live inside of and it
provides all these this management for
you it runs the event loop and that sort
of thing and that's much more of a sort
of framework II notion but the
composition of those frameworks together
form a platform that you can you can use
to solve your problem because everybody
needs a UI everybody needs you know some
componentization and some some runtime
elements that sort of thing do you think
that in this setting if frameworks are
becoming smaller
yeah that's a good question I think some
I think that as because primary because
I view framers as being somewhat more
prescriptive they tend to be more
focused on particular for example in a
UI world a particular workflows you know
here's a framework for doing dialogues
or wizards right so it's that workflow
and and whereas perhaps in the past
maybe the frameworks were a bit larger
and and gave you had a broader scope so
I think maybe what we're seeing is a
component ization of frameworks if I can
say that right I start breaking them
down into smaller frameworks and that's
good because it allows the frameworks to
give it again going back to this notion
of composition it allows people to
assemble frameworks in a in a way that
better suits their requirements so I
might have three or four different
dialogue frameworks or wizard frameworks
and depending on the workflow I'm trying
to give my users I might choose from
those but the overall collection of that
set of frameworks I sort of view as a
platform because it's the stuff you know
it's again it's all that stuff I can
take and use in building my my solution
I think it's it's more moving away from
these old very huge application
frameworks containing everything more
into platforms consisting em out of a
set of smaller frameworks that you can
compose or maybe maybe not compose if
you don't don't like - yeah I think
that's that's generally the the trend
that I I see people sort of people
moving like I say to the finer grain
pieces and composing the bits of
functional functional 'ti that suit
their particular purpose so you know if
you think way back to the I can't
remember the name right now but the the
whole Mac application frameworks you
know those were very broad and and you
know provided a very rich environment
but it was a rich environment for that
you know relatively constrained set of
applications that was great for Mac end
users because they got common look and
feel and consistency and everything but
that's not good as a widely used generic
no platform that people are going to
apply in many different ways do you
think there there there exist different
kind of platforms so you talk about
platform for for very view for more
generic application building maybe so
other different kind of platforms from
your point of view it so I think there
are many different platforms but I'm not
sure that they're really different in
terms of kind it's more in terms of
content so you know I think platform
itself the notion of platform has some
particular characteristics about it and
we certainly within Eclipse see you know
the rich client platform the IDE
platform platform is built on top of
that people like you know the famous
example is the NASA guys and maestro and
ensemble is that their platforms for
building particular kinds of space
mission software applications and
they've gotten together and and a whole
groups of diverse people have come
together to put various pieces of
function into their platform and then
perhaps those same people or others take
that platform and build applications for
particular for particular missions in
the same way that people come to the IDE
platform at Eclipse and build Java
tooling or C tooling or PHP tooling or
or whatever so I don't see them as being
you know I think definitely there are
domain-specific platforms but I think
that's just a difference in the content
if we think about developing platforms
do you think what are the main
differences between to developing the
platform and developing just general
applications or maybe applications on
top of platforms right
so there's there's a few things it's
kind of funny the the guys on the team
on the equinox team sort of teased me
about this but I absolutely mantras that
I or three three things that I always
juxtapose with each other and one is
producer versus consumer I'll talk about
these in a second I'll just enumerate
them here so one is producer versus
consumer another is mechanism
versus policy and the final one is
product versus plugin and it really
comes down to the mindset that you have
while you're you're developing your code
whatever it is so if you're developing
for a platform versus developing for an
application you you really do need to
know which hats you have on and what
things you're building
so just to loop back here to know that
the producer versus consumer whenever
you're writing a piece of function and
making a decision about that piece of
function it do you do well to sort of
think well what hat do I have on here am
i taking the view of the consumer of
this function or am i just producing
some function and I'm not really trying
to constrain or make too many
assumptions about how it's going to be
consumed so a classic example here is
something like menu entry placement so a
guy in Eclipse writes in action actions
are the things that show up in menu
entries and on toolbars and and control
keys and that sort of thing no commands
like that kind of stuff and when you
write one and you and you you implement
the function that you know the
implementation of the run method so
that's cool you're implementing that
you're clearly a producer you know
you're writing something somebody's
going to call run if there's going to be
an active selection or whatever you're
going to do some operation on that
selection and that's your action that's
good
strictly a producer point of view when
it comes down to
then contributing that in say a plug-in
XML in eclipse you have the mechanism of
declaratively expressing extensions to
the UI for example so you can
declaratively express that this action
should have this label with this icon
and should show up at a particular spot
on in the menu hierarchy when you do
that your you flipped over and now your
app your consumer because you're placing
that function in a particular spot that
only is going to make sense in a
particular class of applications or
consumption scenarios so it's it's very
important to distinguish between those
two and when you mix them you end up
with functionality that can't be reused
beyond the scope of of the the original
viewpoint because you had a producer us
or a consumer viewpoint when you
actually place those things so you know
going all the way back to the rich
client platform and the evolution of it
a lot of what happened there was people
looking at the IDE platform that was
eclipse
you know 2.0 2.1 and saying well oh you
know i don't want a file save menu
because my banking application doesn't
it doesn't make sense to have file save
and so a lot of the work that was done
in producing RCP was generic it was was
taking the consumer hat off is we had
the consumer hat of being an IDE
consumer of this infrastructure we took
that hat off and put on a producer hat
and said look I'm gonna provide a
mechanism for placing menu entries and
you can place your menu in trees
wherever you want and I'm going to give
you some pre-canned menus or actions for
example that you can use so just to
simplify your life but you can place
them wherever you want and and you know
so we really separate between producer
and consumer mm-hmm
for mechanism versus policy this is
really a friend of or related to
producer versus consumer because you
know we talked about the action
mechanism and the mechanism for plugging
actions in and defining where they are
and that sort of thing but then there's
a
you would apply on top of that as a
consumer a policy that says oh well I
can place menu entries here and I can
give them these labels and and that sort
of that sort of stuff so the by for
consumers us or producers when you're
producing something if you separate
clearly between mechanism and policy
then your consumers have more power
because they then have a richer policy
set that they can use when they're
defining say like an example of you know
men the menu placement another example
that came up fairly recently in our
development of p2 the the new
provisioning work that's going on at
Eclipse any in Equinox we had this
mechanism or we had this this code we
had several copies of this code that was
watching directories and looking at
directories and watching for changes you
know you put some plugins in there and
we would discover them and we would do
things to them and stuff like that and
there were a number of scenarios and we
had essentially copies of this code that
was doing the same thing and when we sat
back and looked at it we really realized
that there was there's one base
mechanism the directory watcher and
there were a set of policies that talked
about you know where to watch what
directories to watch when to watch do i
watch just at startup do i watch after
startup do I pull how often do I pull
that sort of thing and then what do I do
when I when I see that there's something
changed
do I just generate metadata do i
generate metadata and install do I ask
the user you all those kinds of things
those are policy statements and what our
challenge was as implementers our
producers was to produce the mechanism
that would enable those policies to be
enacted so that's a very powerful
distinction and the the final of the the
three sets of things I talked about you
know product versus plugin this is
really putting on different hats of you
know am I writing sets of functions so
plugins that are sets of function or am
I writing a product and when you are
writing sets of function you you try to
again separate between mechanism and
policy and put on a producer hat
so you're not trying to place things in
menu entries you're not trying to define
the exact semantics of or behaviors of
when you look and what you do and that
sort of thing that's the job of a
product producer so product producers
have the ability to were the ability to
and requirement of worrying about
placement of things workflows
organization of elements branding all of
those kinds of things is the composition
problem whereas as the product or plugin
writer story they're more concerned with
the policy mechanism API extensibility
all of those kinds of ideas it was kind
of a long-winded - you know description
or comment on your earlier question
about the difference between platforms
and applications but I think it is
actually a very important important
element to consider when you're writing
software sounds like like you're
thinking a lot about building api's and
in thinking about how the API should
look like for for the application
developer that is using the platform so
how important is the API design for for
building platform
I think it's it's critical API design
you know sort of impacts everything from
your ability to you know how flexible
something is to your ability to evolve
it and maintain backward compatibility
it really speaks to the quality I guess
if you if you want to say it that way of
the platform you know whether or not a
platform is good you know triggers on a
number of things but many of them come
around you know the quality of the API
how concise it is you know having big
verbose api's with multiple ways of
doing things tends to be very confusing
for for consumers and tends to be very
hard to maintain so you know the
elements of API well we could go on for
a long time about that but the DIA API
is critical to to creating a good
platform yeah maybe we can come back to
the API questions later
especially when we maybe talk about
backward compatibility which they're
interesting I think for building
platforms so what do you think what
makes platform what makes a platform a
good platform well like I was saying I
think primarily it's it's a quality
api's ease of programming so it has to
be consumable so easy to compose pieces
in the case of Eclipse I think a lot
about composition and how to put things
together in reasonable ways making that
easy and you know fundamentally if you
were to look at a platform and say well
is this a good platform as it's a bad
platform I think in many ways the proof
is in the pudding and and you say oh
that's kind of an English idiom but the
it's you you look at how many people are
using it to do lots of different things
if you can pick up in our example of our
CP in Eclipse
if you can pick up the rich client
platform from eclipse and and you know
say well is it a good platform well
who's using it what are they doing with
it well that's a pretty broad spectrum
and a lot of people are thinking a lot
of value out of it so you know it's got
its problems for sure there's there's no
doubt about that but I think it really
is a fairly good platform but what what
should I do with a build a platform to
to make it a good platform so I think
there it's key so I think it does come
back down to API but then you might look
at so what are the elements of designing
a good API and in that case one of the
key things is having lots of consumers
early on so we had lots of clients of
your API earlier on because they'll all
come to your set of function whatever it
is with a different viewpoint they'll
all want something different out of it
they'll all expect to use it a different
way
expect different levels of flexibility
and composability extensibility all
those all those sorts of things so by
having lots of different people
interacting on it you get those
viewpoints it's not to say that you're
always going to satisfy all of them 100%
of the time you know you're gonna
hopefully hit a fairly high percentage
of them but having
those viewpoint an understanding that
hey you know somebody might want to use
this thing for something other than an
IDE or something other than this
particular use case that I had in mind
it makes it harder because you're you're
then building a platform you're then
building generic function as opposed to
more specific function and you're having
two separate mechanism from policy which
means you duh you do have to be a little
more rigorous and you have to define
more API or different API but in the end
it becomes much more worthwhile
well more more useful in the end I
believe so this having going back to
your question of how to how to do a good
platform how to create a good platform
having lots of consumers lots of
interaction in a much of it comes back
to communication and interaction so you
know you understand what your consumers
are wanting they're understanding what
you're producing and and you get that
feedback loop and and in the eclipse
project in eclipse project particularly
we are able to do what we call you know
eating our own dog food which is we use
the stuff we produce and that has been
if you really reflect back on on why
that particular team has been successful
personally I think it's it's largely due
to our ability to eat our own dog food
and unfortunately it's a sort of
rarefied situation because you know not
everybody is producing the tools that
they use to produce the tools you know
what I mean is like you know we're doing
a Java development environment written
in Java so of course we can use what we
produced to produce the next version of
of the the environment but if you're
doing you know you know business
integration tools or web tools or a
banking application or whatever you know
you don't really use those things in
your day-to-day implementation of that
application so you need you need people
who do use it and who do consume it and
and will give you that type feedback so
that they'll tell you and it's not just
good enough to have people tell you
things they have to have faith
that what that there's value in them
telling you these things I recently went
through a essentially a beta program for
some some new application and we were
all asked to you know use this new
application and give feedback and we
were given a you know Bugzilla or
whatever a bug reporting system to give
feedback into and that's great I was all
for it right I went and I got the stuff
and I installed it and within about the
first five minutes you know I had ten
bugs entered or you know ten issues that
had come up with that that would really
I thought you know be useful and
improves a socialite you know entering
all these bugs and all her stuff and it
was a complete black hole never a single
word back on any of them I never
understood whether they accepted them
whether they rejected them whether they
were fix them anything and so I just
like well okay well why am i bothering
yeah it's perhaps a bad attitude but
people have to value their time so if
you can instill upon your consumer
community a real sense that what they
think and what they say matters then
they'll give you that feedback and that
feedback is critical it gets your
replacement for being elite your own dog
food essentially mm-hmm and that's
critical to making a good platform in my
mind yeah I agree completely um but it
sounds sounds not like a trivial task
right so for platform YouTube will get
have multiple clients and maybe many
clients and key and you said it's good
to have many clients asking for many
different things but and then you need
to decide what to implement and want to
implement maybe not right yep so you
need to somebody to set the focus for
the platform development or you make
decisions and maybe you you make the
decision that um you will not going to
implement a specific feature that a
client of the platform asked for so they
maybe get disappointed um so what do you
think how how should you deal with this
specific multiple client situation right
yeah so that's that's a really good you
know a good challenge and what I
personally think makes sense is goes
back to this whole communication issue
and if people were and just went back to
the specific thing about putting in
or whatever you know setting in
requirements it's the same thing if
people put in giving you input and just
seeing it essentially vaporize and and
nothing ever happening and they don't
see why then they get discouraged and to
go away if they see that there's a
longer term view so if you have a long
term vision for what it is you're
building and you can effectively
communicate that to people then they
have a they have a context they have
understand where you're going and why
you're behaving the way you're behaving
and why you might not be implementing
the things that they're asking for or or
doing it in the way that they ask for it
if you've been situated in terms of you
know another group and say well okay
here's these you know you two have very
similar requirements your phrasing it
this way your phrasing it this way but
what actually is happening is under the
covers it's the same mechanism and you
just are applying different policies to
it and so we're gonna implement this
mechanism and you know you guys
implement the policy or you know some
way of getting getting them more
involved I find can be useful and it's
also good I think for exercising the API
or reducing your API footprint you guys
if you can make like a lot of eclipse
you know we have started out and we had
something built in or something assumed
let's just say CVS right our CVS support
and it wasn't built in I wasn't plug in
and everything but but pretty much all
the infrastructure and the platform
assumed that you were using CBS and
there was lots of you know sort of
certain tie-ins and and it weren't as
many lifecycle points as other
repository providers might have needed
and so you know that's fine though it
was our first off and then other people
came to the table and said well hey but
wait a second we want to put in you know
subversion or we want to put in
clearcase or we want it cetera et cetera
and you know on the surface it all clean
oh crap we're gonna have to redo this
whole big thing here and and and provide
this extra sort of functionality over
there and
but if you step back and you look at
what what is it they actually need and
it turns out in many cases they just
need a set of hooks or an extensibility
point or they're not a life cycle event
or something like that
where they can hook in their specific
stuff so that's again you know this
policy versus mechanism thing we have a
mechanism that's walking through this
certain set of processes of committing
things to a repository or whatever and
then there are different policies that
different repositories require you know
when you save something the repository
needs to be able to check and validate
that the save is okay that you can you
are actually allowed to say that for
example that's a problem you don't have
in CVS but one that you might have in
clear case and so by identifying that
mechanism the point at which they can do
that in providing a point at which they
can hook in then they can define their
policy to hook in at that point and do
whatever they need so one way to spin
this around is just essentially look at
it as enabling your clients to do what
they need by doing as little as possible
in the in the actual platform but that's
one way to deal with it but but at the
end you you can come into this situation
where you have to to decide which
feature to implement and maybe implement
feature a and feature be not so how do
you how do you decide how do you
prioritize between those those features
from multiple client right yeah I think
that comes back to the long term vision
you know when you when you know what
you're building then you can see off
down the road you know and I'm talking
like five years just a couple years
whatever right something longer than the
next release so that you can understand
if it makes sense if the choices you're
facing which ones makes sense in the
bigger in the broader context of where
you want the the platform or whatever it
is you're producing where you want that
to go and you know so if you're faced
with two teams that you know hold equal
sway over you you know whether it's
monetary or influential or whatever and
and they're both
proposing you know that's a function or
a feature that that is very important to
them
you know ideally you can find some
commonality in there and you can enable
both of them but in cases of actual you
know conflict and where that you can
really only do one or the other you know
that there's so many elements that come
into that decision I don't think there
is a sort of prescriptive answer but but
having a long term vision and knowing
where you're going makes and and then
communicating that to your to these
people so they can understand and
perhaps rephrase their requirements in
the context of this longer-term vision I
think that can help a lot they still can
can end up with them you have just
limited time maybe the requirements are
all all good and all fitting into these
long term vision but you still have
limited time and you need to decide what
to do for the next release or maybe for
the release after the next release sure
and and by having that open discussion
then maybe it's the case that that they
can say well oh you know what I
understand what you're saying and I'm
fine with getting this full set of
function I've been requesting in two
years instead of next year but you know
for next year we really want to do this
so can we trim that down and can we do
this smaller piece that's still on the
roadmap it's still in the right
direction but it's an incremental thing
that they can do and then they can use
to get a get around their immediate
problems okay so how important is
backward compatibility from your point
of view well you know it's it's if you
want to retain your community they get
really upset generally if you start
breaking them every release we see that
a lot in Eclipse and you know we work
really really hard to not break people
and to maintain you know binary backward
compatibility it's it's extremely
difficult and sometimes we fail and and
we get told pretty quickly about those
failures and and you know sometimes it's
there's nothing to do sometimes it was a
mistake and sometimes there was just
nothing else we could do we had to fix
some bugs and that meant breaking
something else in a controlled way
but but generally you know backward
compatibility is extremely important for
platforms and that's what makes them
they're pretty interesting and
challenging to produce is you know you
have to getting there getting your API
right out the front of course is you
know nobody ever gets it done gets it
right the first time you takes you three
times to get it at least to get it close
to being right but doing it in a you
know comes back to the communication
stuff the more you're communicating with
your consumer base the more different
viewpoints you have on it the better
understanding you have of what it is
you're producing then you have a least a
better chance of producing something
that is sustainable and you mentioned it
the term binary compatibility just as
right no can you can it give a short
explanation what do you mean by binary
compatibility and in contrast to maybe
cells compatibility sure sure yeah so
binary compatibility is essentially the
ability to just take a and already
compiled in Eclipse context take an
already compiled bundle and that might
use some function from a lower down
piece and and reuse it without having to
recompile it so the the classes will
load you know all of the Java language
requirements are met so as an example of
something that breaks binary
compatibility is if I as an API designer
produce an API and we'll just call it
foo an interface Java interface called
foo and it has a you know two methods on
it and if my API says or expects that
you as a client will implement that API
so you'll implement you'll make some
class bar that implements foo and as a
require as a result you'll have to
implement those two methods that are on
foo if I then turn around and add a
method to foo then your implementation
of foo will be broken because I'll have
three methods on the definition of food
but you only have two methods on the
implementation of it and that class your
your bar class will no longer even load
into the VM the VM will fail with a
verification error you know at whatever
kind of error at runtime and so that
that's you know clearly breaking your
plugin just will not work it just
doesn't run anymore and and that's you
know that's bad
because you've got all these plugins
shipped out there and people using them
they want to be able to move them from
3.3 to 3.4 etc whatever version for
whatever version source compatibility or
yeah source compatibility is where there
are certain kinds of changes you can do
that aren't obviously changing but
because of the way the Java language or
the Java compiler works being you may
need to recompile something to cause it
to to work again so one easy example of
this one is if you have a constants in
Java
typically declare them as public static
finals something like that you know
public static final string and then you
give it some value in and what happens
at compile time is those those static
finals those public static finals
actually get in line if they don't
become the value gets in lined in the
referring class so they don't it's not
doesn't it's not a reference to a field
someplace so if you change the value of
that field you actually now I have and
I've already compiled my class then I've
got the old value you've got the new
value and if for example there's an
equality test someplace that's that's
checking to see if these two things are
equal it's a course gonna fail if I just
simply recompile my code without doing
any code changes I just recompile it
then I'll we then then I'll be up to
updated because now I'll have a copy of
the new constant value in my class file
and everything will work fine so that's
one of those those things where you know
if you can expect people to just
recompile without doing any code changes
then you can do certain changes that you
know otherwise you wouldn't be able to
because they would break minor and
compatibility do you have some ideas how
to maintain backward compatibility
maybe binary backward compatibility so
what are the key maybe patterns or or
issues you you should take care of if
you if you would like to stay binary
compatibility with your platform
development
right well again it all comes down to
API and having good API and you know
there's a saying good fences make good
neighbors right is if you have clear API
and the API is functional enough that
people don't need to reach in and use
internal stuff then you know as long as
you can maintain that API then your
consumers are happy because they're
basically unaffected by implementation
changes so there's a whole raft of you
know elements that go into designing
good API and an extensible evolvable API
in fact there's a a really good document
that's evolved over the years on the
eclipse wiki I think there's a wiki area
called the API central or I think it's
API central on the the do eclipse wiki
wiki dot Eclipse org and just go there
and search for API central I think it's
called we can put a lake in link in the
show notes okay great great
so I'll make sure that I'll give you the
good link but yeah they there's a whole
bunch of information on the eclipse wiki
that really helps you really talks about
the API evolution issues and you know
what is a what is a problematic thing
like defining a you know like failing to
tell people whether or not a particular
interface should be implemented by
consumers or whether it's expected that
it's just going to be implemented by the
the framework or the platform itself
being very clear about your API there's
a whole bunch of challenges that come
into into play with Java 5 and generics
there's a whole number of gotchas things
that you wouldn't quite expect you know
by specifying generics a certain way you
can inhibit you you can inhibit your
ability to evolve those api's and and
the the documents on the wiki have have
sort of concrete examples it's much
easier to see in code so I don't don't
really want to go through trying to
describe them
you know I'm waving my hands frantically
here but you can of course can't see
that so it's not going to help at all
so yeah so back to your original
question about making a P I know sorry
evolvable api's so I think the the
number of pitfalls and issues that are
enumerated on the wiki those you know
those ones are good and it a lot of what
we talk about too comes back to
communication and making sure you have
lots of interaction on it and
completeness of the of the contract API
is essentially a contract and the
completeness of that contract definition
is very important and one of the other
things that we see that comes to play
here is you know not all API is sort of
or you know crystal clear in the sense
that it's not crisp as to who ought to
be using this and in many cases once
we've introduced componentization here
we have relationships between components
for example that aren't api
relationships but they're more like a
friendship style relationship we have
this notion in eclipse so it's called ex
friends and so when I X when I have a
package that encapsulates my API and I
want to export that package if I just
want to allow you to use it because you
and I are our collection of you know
form a tight tight collaboration to
produce some sort of function I can say
okay well I can export my package and
then just mark it as X friends Martin
and that means that only you'll be able
to see it in you know SGI you actually
get strong fencing off of API so if you
don't export something at all and you're
in your bundle manifest then it's just
plain old not visible to the outside
world there's nothing they can do that
will allow them to load that to refer to
that those classes from code and so you
know if you have really a couple of
different you can export something in
which case everybody can access it you
can not export something which case
nobody can access it but there's this
middle ground that we need to walk where
I want some friends to be able to access
it so I can export things mark them as
mark it up with who who my friends are
and then those people will be able to
access
and we have an additional mechanism
called ex internal which allows us to
export everything market as internal so
essentially we're telling people that
they ought not use it but in some cases
you know we've got researchers and
innovators who are looking at the IT
clips and saying well I really want to
push it that next step and I really want
to go and and to do that that advanced
stuff they need to be able to reach in
and twiddle around with some internals
and Bill you know they'll feed it back
into the community and say well hey look
at here's what I had to do we need some
new API here or whatever and and so for
the next release or some subsequent
release you know it'll all be fine
and then there are other people who just
like no I'm shipping a product I need to
get this job done I don't have time to
wait for an API evolution which might
take a year or something I just need to
I'm working around a bug I'm doing
whatever I'm gonna reference this
internal and I take full responsibility
for the fact that I might be broken in
the next release because I've referenced
some internal thing so our tooling
supports all of that and and tells you
when you're doing something you ought
not be doing and so I think that's a
critical part of it as well as having
that sort of complete definition of the
API signature for a a bundle as a whole
as a component and getting the feedback
from the IDE that I noticed that oh no
now I'm using some internal stuff
instead of official API right right
because otherwise the automatic import
features from the IDE they're so nice
that I didn't even recognize in which
package class that I'm using is in if
there's an internal in the name or not I
don't I don't know yeah yeah so we've
tended to put internal in the package
names just as a it used to be the rule
and and now we've got X internal our
next friends and and that's really what
defines API Ness you know if something
is exported and it's not marked as X
friends or X internal then it's it's
likely part of the API but actually I
want to touch on something if you just
quickly here because you start talking
about packages and this is something you
know we talked about API evolve ability
and and that sort of thing one thing
we've discovered quite interestingly
over the past few years is that
packaging like jet use the use of java
package
is actually quite important now when I
started out doing Java code I really
didn't pay much attention to it and I
thought I whatever you know it's kind of
like how I want to group it so that I it
looks the classes are together and when
I looked at them and the IDE that kind
of thing you know
driven by by just development tool
issues essentially and what happened is
when we were going through the RCP
effort this is three four years ago we
had cause to refactor a bunch of plugins
so the run time that we had a plugin
called org eclipse core runtime and we
had another plug-in called organ clips
UI and those you know as the name sort
of imply were the runtime and the UI you
know basic pieces for Eclipse and we
needed to refactor those in the course
of doing our RCT efforts what happened
was in side of each of those bundles we
had packages that had multiple concerns
mixed into them so in the runtime
package we had the plug-in model we had
the extension registry we had a bunch of
infrastructure pieces you know just
helper classes and exceptions and stuff
like that and a number of other pieces
all mixed into the package that's called
org Eclipse core runtime and so when we
went to refactor our bundle and split
those all apart we ended up with with
that package being split across multiple
bundles and while technologically that's
okay in in OSGi can can handle that to a
certain degree it it's got a number of
problems first of all there's there are
some runtime issues and in terms of
dependencies and and how you can specify
things because osg is unit of delivery
is bundles but as unit of dependency
it's finest grain of dependency is
packages so I can specify a dependency
on a particular package but if there are
three copies of that package laying
around in the system
you know OSGi doesn't have any really
decent way of figuring that out right I
mean there are somehow there are some
things you can do but it starts to get
really messy and it's also from a design
point of view you know if you think of
packages as having some
there's some reason why he gave it a
name and that that name you know likely
has some meaning so if that's true then
we know why do you have that same
meaning that same name split over
multiple bundles presumably those are
different things so the the lesson to
take out of this is that you should
really think about your package naming
carefully and what you put into what
package and think of it in terms of
separation of concerns and you know what
I you know we should have separated out
our utility classes from our real
functional classes and we should have
separated our out the extension registry
classes or types from the plugin
definition types and there's good
reasons why we didn't in some cases and
in other cases it was laziness but you
know now I find I have a lot more
packages because I'm much more aware of
this oh well that package actually is
something completely different and I
might want to be able to move that into
a separate bundle as an example so
that's something that helps you evolve
your API so that once you've done a
change you can end up with you know
names that make sense because now we
have a bunch of package names that don't
make sense anymore because the context
has changed so you know that's just one
of those those things if you can't
change a package name without breaking
API mmm right but it seems to me that
there are relatively few changes that I
can do to the API without breaking the
client right right so there's things you
can do to mitigate some of that so for
example if you have an interface going
back to our example before where you
have an interface that you're expecting
somebody to implement by providing an
abstract superclass that they can use
mm-hmm then then if you add you know my
example was I added another method to
the interface well then I can add the if
my expectation is that all clients will
extend some abstract class that I give
them then I can add that method with a
default implementation to the abstract
class and I won't have broken anybody so
I would point people back at the wiki
page and you know it talks about a lot
of these issues and and and there's also
some good tutorials they do every year
pretty much there's an API tutorial at
eclipse Khan and
it's generally very well received and
it's very well done so that material is
also available so I assume they're there
as well mentioned these these techniques
like compatibility layers and versioned
interfaces and stuff like that yeah okay
yeah that's cool so I did want to
mention one thing because it's it's a
bit of a plug for a tool that that's
just coming into eclipse and so we've
started we've recognized really this
this importance of API and in Eclipse
three for the release that's coming up
in June there's some API tooling and and
what this really is is it does a number
of different things one is that it helps
you understand when you broke an API so
given some baseline so for example if
you take eclipse 3.3 and we're currently
developing eclipse 3.4 and you say well
okay three point four should not break
any API that's in three point three so
it takes three three is my baseline and
then it analyzes your current code just
a three for code against the three three
code compares all the signatures and all
the other things that go into binary
compatibility and tells you as you're
developing the code whether or not
you've broken compatibility so in my
example earlier with the interface that
I added in method two as soon as I saved
that interface the API tooling would
come back and say hey wait wait wait
wait you can't do that you just broke
compatibility all right oh you know darn
you're right so that that's one aspect
of it
another aspect is finding all references
to some some of your code and of course
there's Java search and and that sort of
thing but it requires you to have all of
the code you might not always have all
the code for all your consumers so for
example you know if you're working in a
large organization that has many
products based on Eclipse you're not
likely to have all of those those things
installed on your machine or available
to your IDE while you're developing code
but you can with the API tooling
essentially get a an API reference
signature or footprint from all of those
products that's much much smaller than
the original code and you can have that
available and then you can do searches
for references and what you end up
getting told is it
oh yes there's a bundle over here and it
references this that method or that
field or that type and so that's really
handy for the cases where you're either
a trying to find out how use how broadly
used as an API so you oh wow look I've
had a thousand people use this okay it's
really important I can't you know don't
wanna I want to find out more about how
they're using it or something
or there's some API you think that
nobody ought to be using and so you say
well why is somebody using that and they
go off to that team and find out what
they're doing or those places where
you've got internal code that you want
to change but you want to be aware that
there might be somebody you know you're
trying to be friendly and realize that
some people are using internal stuff and
so you you go and you can do a check and
say well who's using this internal
method or this internal type and you can
you can discover those references and
then there's a third element to the API
tooling that is version number evolution
and so in Eclipse we have version
numbers on our packages and version
numbers on our bundles and those version
numbers have semantics it's sort of like
it reflects the the rate of change or
the kind of change in a in a bundle and
and or package and so what the API
tooling will do is say well you know
what you just changed this bundle in
this way which means you should have
evolved your version number you should
have changed like the second segment in
divergent number or something like that
and so it'll tell you that's going to
help you maintain those signatures and
then other people can specify their
dependencies appropriately oh cool yeah
that sounds cool but but it sounds like
we could record a whole episode on this
API design and and backward
compatibility topic right yeah I I think
so yes I think we should we should close
this episode and maybe you would like to
give some some kind of pearls of wisdom
to our listeners some some closing notes
well and I hope that I've given that few
pearls of wisdom already but I guess the
the thing I'd say about platforms in
general is you know in essence equinox
and the the base pieces of Eclipse are
platform for building platform that's
it's or maybe even you look at as a
framework for building platforms I'm not
sure but it really is this you know
platforms are I'm seeing it more and
more and for certain degree it's maybe
I'm just attuned to them now but I see
the platforms coming up in all sorts of
different industries platforms have the
ability to be transformational both
within a business but also within a
whole industry I mean the Eclipse IDE
itself pretty much changed the landscape
of software tooling at least you know
for a large chunk of it I mean they used
to have a lot of different tools and now
we've really got Eclipse Microsoft and
Sun and you know we've really kind of
changed that whole landscape by building
a platform that other people could use
and I think RCP also has a similar
effect and then in particular domains
you know I talked about it in the NASA
context with the space mission software
and it really is changing the way that
they're developing their their software
to great effect and I see that in other
industries people that I've been working
with recently you know doing things in
their industry where the well the
healthcare guys is an example they you
know healthcare software is very
fragmented and very proprietary and
locked in stuff and and you know now
people are starting to see the value in
a platform let's get together all the
stuff we're all doing the same common
commodity pieces let's just get together
build a platform and then we can step up
a level and build the things that were
good at build the things that we have
domain knowledge or that are domain
specific and raise the level both of our
code what we're doing and also the level
of what our users see because now they
don't have to you know now they have
world-class UI is because they don't
have you eyes that were built by a bunch
of people who you know don't really know
how to build you eyes in it that's
because it's hard right but bill you you
you mentioned the healthcare guys and
this brings me to the to the idea of um
how does this platform building relates
to product line engineering so we had
some several episodes on product line
engineering and the people there
mentioned that ok building platform sets
that's the old way doing product line
engineering techniques is
the better idea so what is your opinion
what do you think do you have an opinion
on that uh well I'm not so familiar I
guess with the details of what it means
to do product line engineering but at
least superficially it seems like
they're very much related you know I
think that platforms that are tailored
to specific domains or specific types of
applications you know may well just be
another way of talking about product
line engineering elements I'm not sure
okay any other pearls of wisdom for the
yen yeah I think you know API and
communication just to recap you know you
get better API by communicating more and
interacting more with your consumers
listening to them and you know don't be
afraid to say no right it's it's it's
you've got to say no to maintain the
integrity of your API and you've got to
say no so you keep the communication
channels open just leaving a go silence
leaves people in limbo and they don't
know whether they need to find another
option or or whether their problem is
going to be solved for them so
communication is key and you know highly
released early release often get that
interaction and the feedback and and
shoot for people to help you you know
eat your dog food right and and you have
to get in their boat to to pretend that
you're eating your own dog food
essentially great thank you very very
much for being on the show Jeff okay
thank you it's been a lot of fun
[Music]
thanks for downloading and listening to
software engineering radio software
engineering radio is an educational
program brought to you by hillside
Europe if you want more information
about the podcast and all the other
episodes visit our website and s/ii -
radio dotnet if you want to support us
you can donate to the SE radio team via
the website or you can advertise for su
radio for example by clicking on the
Digg reddit delicious and Slashdot
buttons to contact the team please send
email to team at s e - radio net or if
it is specific to an episode please use
the comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under
Creative Commons 2.5 licence please see
the website for details thanks to
Charlie Crowell and the pulsate Music
Network for the music used in the show
the song is called Vegas hard rock
shuffle
[Music]